I don't have anything close to a daily
routine, per say. Every morning is different
and I'm completely unable to follow
through with most repetitive practices.
Most of my days are work days where very little
interesting happens. However, now and then,
when I'm all caught up, a day off is in
order. A day reserved to rise with the sun,
to simply be, to do exactly what I love to do
for every minute of it. These days are holy ones,
in which time loses its meaning. If you have
ever experienced a day where you forget about
the passing hours due to pure enjoyment of what
you're doing, you know how special it can be.
When I spend enough time wandering the cascades,
I lose myself. Maybe I simply stepped into a
fairy circle, but suddenly everything happens
at a gentle pace. There's no ticking clock to
remind me of the hours that rule our lives. I'm
completely connected to a world of my own design,
relishing the beauty of the alpine flowers. I
wander and wander, and mutter to myself as random
thoughts go through my head. For example, wouldn't
the yellow bells make fantastic hats for fairies?
And with that, suddenly it's the
evening and the day has passed me
by.
I once read a book about a little boy.
He lived very long ago when there were
few people on this earth. He was part of a
tribe who lived by the sun and the seasons.
These people didn't have minutes or seconds.
The child saw this and thought that he could
help his people if he measured the days to better
predict the future: the best days for hunting,
the best days for berry picking. He invented
a crude version of a sundial, and he marked
the hours. This new knowledge excited him, and
soon he began to mark shorter periods of time...
As a grown man he marked the minutes, as a
white bearded elder he marked the seconds.
And suddenly his final day on earth presented
itself, and he wept that he had never realized
that despite how he counted his days he had
not stopped to think that his days were already
counted. He had let them slip through his fingers.
And with his final breath he warned his people to
be careful of how they use the knowledge
of time, lest it rule over their lives.
I read the story, initially, when I was a child
and unfortunately I can't remember the book I
read it in. But that little boy stayed with me,
there's so many sayings in my culture that pertain
to time. Words like “be efficient, don't waste
your time” “time is money” “you're losing
time” or, perhaps, the most terrifying:
“don't waste the best time of your life”.
It gives time an enormous power over
us, as if we need to fear misusing it.
I don't think this is necessarily
wrong, as our lives are very precious,
but I do think that sometimes we put an
overly high value on being productive
and using our time in a way that achieves a goal
such as having a highly productive morning routine
that I absolutely cannot follow through with, no
matter how hard I try. In fact, maybe just sitting
or thinking or not doing anything particular at
all can be a very productive use of our time.
Advertisements often suggest ways to
save time and live more efficiently,
as if that should be our ultimate goal,
after spending a day wandering the mountains
I think I've had one of the
most productive days of my life,
and I have nothing to show for it except a
pinecone and the speckled shell of a quail's egg.
But I felt truly free, and know that I didn't
waste one second simply enjoying the day.
I hope you take some time to simply forget what
you're doing tomorrow, or the day after, and
disconnect from the clock. You may be surprised
by what you find. Have a lovely day or night 🤍